<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Maths & Physics Club</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io" />
<updated>2017-08-13T01:17:24+05:30</updated>
<id>http://mnp-club.github.io/</id>
<author>
  <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
  <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
  <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bazinga!!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-physics/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-physics</id>
  <published>2017-08-04T23:29:43+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-08-04T23:29:43+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Physics is a 3 round quiz where the participant have to rack their brains and use simple intuitive physics concept to solve questions. The questions can be explaining a simple everyday phenomenon to solving some mind-bending thought experiment. Join in and lets enjoy the true essence of physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--la-101&quot;&gt;Venue : LA 101&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-9th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 9th August&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-physics/&quot;&gt;Bazinga!!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 04, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bazinga!!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-maths/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-maths</id>
  <published>2017-08-04T23:29:43+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-08-04T23:29:43+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Maths is a quiz where teams compete to solve an assortment of problems from buzzer round and challenge questions to deep thought problems. While the solutions are based on elementary concepts, they’re sure to test your creativity and challenge your reasoning skills!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--la-101&quot;&gt;Venue : LA 101&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-10th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 10th August&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/events/bazinga-maths/&quot;&gt;Bazinga!!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 04, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physics Detective]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/events/physics-detective/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/events/physics-detective</id>
  <published>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;A fan of Sherlock and Physics ? This is the perfect combination of the two as you use your physics’ knowledge to try to solve puzzles and riddles in a competition to see who is the true Physics Detective!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-20th-september&quot;&gt;Date: 20th September&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Time: To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/events/physics-detective/&quot;&gt;Physics Detective&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 03, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math Olympics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/events/math-olympics/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/events/math-olympics</id>
  <published>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-28th-september&quot;&gt;Date: 28th September&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Time: To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/events/math-olympics/&quot;&gt;Math Olympics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 03, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Logic GC]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/events/logic-gc/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/events/logic-gc</id>
  <published>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-08-03T23:29:43+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-21st-october&quot;&gt;Date: 21st October&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-saturday&quot;&gt;Day: Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Time: To be decided&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/events/logic-gc/&quot;&gt;Logic GC&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 03, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cryptography]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/cryptography/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/cryptography</id>
  <published>2017-07-21T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-07-21T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Raghav Goyal</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>goyal61@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;You connect your phone to a computer and a message pops up saying, “trust or don’t trust this computer” What is this trust? Why can you download only certified apps ? How do you get to talk over email, what makes you so sure that you can share your bank details over the internet? Raghav Goyal studies the basics of cryptography, which includes historic encryption methods from the world war II to modern times and a lot more . You can find a report of his learnings here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bits-and-public-key-systems&quot;&gt;Bits and Public key Systems:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bit Strings&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern ciphers do not involve letter substitutions. They tend to use an encoding scheme to convert the message into a sequence of binary digits. The most commonly used encoding scheme is probably ASCII. This bit sequence representing the plaintext is then encrypted to give the ciphertext as a bit sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ASCII requires eight bits to represent one character, and so for a block cipher that has 64-bit blocks, the encryption algorithm acts on eight characters at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following sequence of 12 bits: 100111010110. If we split into blocks of size 3 we get: 100 111 010 110, our sequence becomes 4 7 2 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;000=0, 001=1, 010=2, 011 = 3, 100=4, 101=5, 110=6, 111 = 7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common way of writing bit-strings is to use the hexadecimal notation (HEX). For HEX the string is divided into blocks of size 4 with the following representation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0000 = 0 0100 = 4 1000 = 8 1100 = C&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0001 = 1 0101 = 5 1011 = 9 1101 = D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0010 = 2 0110 = 6 1010 = A 1101 = E&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0011 = 3 0111 = 7 1011 = B 1111 = F&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Symmetric cryptography:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) stream cipher       b) block cipher&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stream cipher encrypts bits individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encryption and decryption are simple additions modulo 2 (aka XOR)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Encryption and decryption are the same functions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Encryption: yi =esi(xi )=xi +si mod2 xi ,yi ,si ∈{0,1}   • Decryption: xi =esi(yi )=yi +si mod2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modulo 2 addition is equivalent to XOR operation (Nice way of encryption)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• For perfectly random key stream si , each ciphertext output bit has a 50% chance to be 0     or 1 .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Inverting XOR is simple, since it is the same XOR operation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-06-02-at-10-03-06-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;XOR Truth table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Block Ciphers:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always encrypt a full block (several bits)
Are common for Internet applications
Initially it was thought, best way to secure a system is to keep the encryption and decryption secret from the public! However recently its been realised that encrytion and decryption algorithms should be kept open reason is, its the only way to be sure that the functions used are secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This highlights a potential weakness for stream ciphers because anyone who is able to launch a known plaintext attack can deduce parts of the keystream sequence from the corresponding plaintext and ciphertext bit pairs. Thus, users of stream ciphers must protect against attacks where the attacker deduces part of the keystream&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Block ciphers can be used to provide confidentiality, data integrity, or user authentication, and can even be used to provide the keystream generator for stream ciphers. As with stream ciphers, it is very difficult to give a precise assessment of their security. If an attacker has obtained a known plaintext and ciphertext pair for an unknown key, then that should not enable them to deduce easily the ciphertext corresponding to any other plaintext block. This is just one reason for requiring a block cipher to satisfy the &lt;b&gt;diffusion property&lt;/b&gt; which is that a small change in the plaintext, maybe for example in one or two positions, should produce an unpredictable change in the ciphertext. Block ciphers should satisfy the confusion property which is, in essence, that if an attacker is conducting an exhaustive key search then there should be no indication that they are ‘near’ to the correct key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest, and perhaps the most natural, way to apply a block cipher to a long message is to divide the binary sequence into blocks of appropriate size and then to encrypt each block individually and independently. When this occurs we say we are using the &lt;b&gt;Electronic Code Book mode&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;ECB mode&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these potential dangers of using a block cipher in ECB mode can be removed by arranging for the encryption of each individual block to depend on all the message blocks that precede it in the message. If this is done, then identical message blocks almost certainly give distinct cryptogram blocks, and manipulation of the cryptogram is likely to result in meaningless messages after decryption has been applied. There are two standard ways of effecting this. They are known as &lt;b&gt;Cipher Feedback (CFB) mode&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;Cipher Block Chaining (CBC) mode&lt;/b&gt; and are discussed later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large messages need to be condensed into short bit-strings, it is inevitable that more than one message can give rise to the same shorter bit- string and this automatically implies that the process is irreversible. These functions are known as &lt;b&gt;hash functions&lt;/b&gt; and, depending on the application, they may or may not involve the use of a cryptographic key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea of a hash function is that the resultant hash value is a condensed representative image of the message. The hashed value has a number of names including digital fingerprint, message digest, or, not surprisingly, a hash. Hashing has a number of applications, including the provision of data integrity and as part of the digital signature process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a public key cryptosystem each entity has a public key and a corresponding private key. These keys are chosen so that it is practically impossible to deduce the private key from the public key. Anyone wishing to use this system to send a secret message to someone else needs to obtain that person’s public key and use it to encrypt the data. It is also worth observing that when a public key system is used to provide confidentiality then, since the public encryption key is widely known and can be used by everyone, the ciphertext does not provide any authentication of the sender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a public key system both the &lt;b&gt;algorithm and the encryption key are public&lt;/b&gt;. Thus an attacker is faced with the task of trying to deduce the message from the cryptogram. Encryption process needs to be chosen very carefully. Genuine receiver needs to be able to decrypt easily. Thus the process must be chosen so that knowledge of the decryption key facilitates the determination of the message from the cryptogram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;perfect-secrecy&quot;&gt;Perfect Secrecy:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An Example:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that Mr X is about to make a decision that will have serious repercussions on the share value of a company. If he makes the decision ‘buy’ then the shares will increase in value, but the decision ‘sell’ will result in a collapse in their value. Clearly anyone who received this decision before the broker would have the opportunity to use that information to either make a profit or avoid a disastrous loss, depending on the decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to protect their interests, he and his broker decide to encrypt the message that will convey the decision. One option might be to use a Simple Substitution Cipher that, as we have already noted, is usually sufficient for protecting short messages. Knowledge of the length of the cryptogram would be sufficient to give the interceptor 100 per cent confidence that he knew the message, even though he could not determine the key used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option might be to use the following system in which the two keys, k1 and k2, are equally likely. In order to describe the complete algorithm we use a standard notation. For key k1, the ciphertext for the plaintext message BUY is 0 while the ciphertext for SELL is 1. To express this simply we write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ek1 (BUY) = 0 and Ek1 (SELL) = 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete cipher is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Key k1: Ek1 (BUY) = 0, Ek1 (SELL) = 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Key k2: Ek2 (BUY) = 1, Ek2 (SELL) = 0&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that, in essence, before the cryptogram was intercepted the attackers’ only option was to try to guess the message. Once the cryptogram was received, they could also guess the key. Since the number of keys is the same as the number of messages, the chances of either guess being correct are equal. This is &lt;b&gt;perfect secrecy&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;One-time Pad&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic example of a &lt;b&gt;perfectly secure cipher system&lt;/b&gt; is the one-time pad. If the message is a passage of English text containing &lt;b&gt;n letters&lt;/b&gt; with all punctuation and spaces removed, then the key, which is only used once to protect a single message, is a randomly generated sequence of n letters from the alphabet. The encryption rule is precisely that used for the &lt;b&gt;Vigenère Cipher&lt;/b&gt; with the key replacing the keyword. Thus, if we associate each letter A to Z with the numbers 0 to 25 in the usual way, for message m1, m2,…, mn and key k1, k2,…, kn, the ith component of the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cryptogram is given by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;ci = (mi + ki) mod 26&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another common version of this algorithm often called a &lt;b&gt;Vernam Cipher&lt;/b&gt; where the alphabet used is &lt;b&gt;binary&lt;/b&gt;, that is 0 and 1, and the cryptogram is obtained by adding the message and key modulo 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the one-time pad is that, since the keystreams are random, it is impossible to generate the same keystream simultaneously at both the sender and receiver. Thus they require a second secure channel for distributing the random keys&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Problem:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementers of the communications system are now faced with a potentially difficult problem. How does the receiver obtain this random sequence? Since the sequence is randomly generated it is ‘impossible’ for the sender and receiver to generate the same key simultaneously. One-time pads can only be used if the communicators have a second secure means of exchanging information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types-of-ciphers&quot;&gt;Types of ciphers:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modern application of cryptography&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNU pg
Tru-crypt
Secure shell
plugin for thunderbird
cell phone
bank cards
VPN
IPOD
kindle
Even our mobiles, GSM was one of the best advances in cryptography. Voice encryption basically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Caesar Cipher&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caesar Cipher described each of the letters A to W is encrypted by being represented by the letter that occurs three places after it in the alphabet. (shift of 3). here shift can be by any number and it is vulnerable to attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let k, x, y ε {0,1, …, 25}
• Encryption: y=ek(x)≡x+kmod26      • Decryption: x=dk(x)≡y-kmod26&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Affine cipher&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving caesars cipher
y=(a.x+b) mod26&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Simple Substitution Ciphers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although having a &lt;b&gt;large number of keys is a necessary&lt;/b&gt; requirement for cryptographic security, it is important to stress that having a large number of keys is certainly no guarantee that the cipher system is strong. The discussion of this cipher establishes the dangers of relying on a large number of keys as an indication of strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-11-at-12-12-58-pm.png?w=739&quot; alt=&quot;English text frequencies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Simple Substitution Cipher is used each specific letter of the alphabet is replaced by the same substituted letter. Thus if, for example, we use a cipher where R replaces E, then the frequency of R in the cryptogram is equal to the frequency of E in the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of keys for a Simple Substitution Cipher is equal to the number of ways in which the 26 letters of the alphabet can be arranged. It is called 26 factorial and is denoted by 26!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;note that there is a 200-page novel that does not use the letter E (Gilbert Adair’s translation of A Void by Georges Perec).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;adPlayfair cipher&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Playfair  is an example of a &lt;b&gt;‘Bigram‘&lt;/b&gt; Cipher. This means that letters are encrypted in pairs, as opposed to individually. The key is a 5 by 5 square (with entries comprised of the 25 letters obtained by &lt;b&gt;deleting J&lt;/b&gt; from the alphabet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before encrypting using a Playfair Cipher the message has to be &lt;b&gt;rearranged&lt;/b&gt; slightly. To do this you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;replace J’s with I’s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;write message in pairs of letters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;do not allow identical pairs – if they occur insert Z between them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if the number of letters is odd, add Z to the end&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-11-at-12-44-25-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We extend the key by adding a sixth column and a sixth row to the original key. The sixth row is identical to the first row, while the sixth column is identical to the first column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-11-at-12-47-51-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rule for encryption is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the two letters lie in the same row of the key then each letter is replaced by the one on its right in the extended key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If two letters lie in the same column of the key then each letter is replaced by the one below it in the extended key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the two letters are not in the same row or column then the first letter is replaced by the letter that is in the row of the first letter and the column of the second letter. The second letter is replaced by the fourth corner of the rectangle formed by the three letters used so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now encrypt the message: GOOD BROOMS SWEEP CLEAN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;GO OD BR OZ OM SZ SW EZ EP CL EA NZ&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete cryptogram is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;FP UT EC UW PO DV TV BV CM BG CS DY&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Homophonic Coding&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing some extra characters so that, for ex, the plaintext letter E is represented by more than one ciphertext character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These extra characters are known as randomizing elements and the process of &lt;b&gt;expanding the alphabet is called homophonic coding&lt;/b&gt;. As an illustration we might introduce a cipher where the alphabet for the cryptogram would be the numbers 00, 01, 02,…, 31. Each cryptogram number represents a unique plaintext letter but the letters A, E, N, O, R, T are each represented by two distinct letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-30-at-1-49-35-pm.png?w=739&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Polyalphabetic Ciphers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a homophonic cipher is used, the frequency histogram of the cryptogram is made flatter by increasing the size of the alphabet. This ensures that more than one ciphertext character may represent the same plaintext character. However, it is still true that each ciphertext character represents a unique plaintext character and there is always the danger of an attacker compiling a dictionary of known plaintext and ciphertext pairs for a given key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vigènere Ciphers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vigenère Cipher is probably the best known of the ‘manual’ polyalphabetic ciphers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-11-at-1-50-13-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common methods for using the square to obtain a cipher&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Message : &lt;b&gt;P L A I N T E X T&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key : &lt;b&gt;f r e d f r e d f&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encrypt the initial letter P we use the key letter beneath it which, in this case, is f. Thus to encrypt P we go to the row of the square determined by f and read off the letter beneath P, which is U. Similarly we encrypt L by taking the letter underneath it in the row determined by r, which is C. The process for encrypting P with key letter f is illustrated here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Transposition Ciphers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our example the key is a small number. We use &lt;b&gt;5 as the key&lt;/b&gt;. In order to encrypt a message using this key, we write the key in rows of 5 letters and encrypt by writing the letters of the first column first, then the second column etc. If the length of the message is not a multiple of 5 then we add the appropriate number of Zs at the end before we encrypt. The process is most easily understood by working through a small example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encrypt the message WHAT WAS THE WEATHER LIKE ON FRIDAY. Since the key is 5 the first step involves writing the message in rows of 5 letters. This is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHATW ASTHE WEATH ERLIK EONFR IDAY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the length of the message is not a multiple of 5, we must add one Z to get: WHATW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ASTHE WEATH ERLIK EONFR IDAYZ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now read down &lt;b&gt;each column&lt;/b&gt; in turn to get the following cryptogram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WAWEEIHSERODATALNATHUFYWEHKRZ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;SUPER ENCRYPTION&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combination of two or more ciphers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, say, we want to super-encrypt using a Simple Substitution Cipher and a Transposition Cipher, then we first encrypt the message using the Simple Substitution Cipher, and then encrypt the resultant cryptogram using the Transposition Cipher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;basics-of-cryptography&quot;&gt;Basics of cryptography:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-05-28-at-5-40-07-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attacker is only able to break an algorithm if they have sufficient information to enable them to recognize the correct key or, more frequently, to identify incorrect keys. It is important to realize that this extra information is likely to be crucial to the attacker. Suppose, for instance, that they know the plaintext was English text, and that the decryption of some ciphertext using a guessed key does not give meaningful English plaintext. In this case, the guessed key must be incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cipher system is called &lt;b&gt;symmetric&lt;/b&gt; if it &lt;b&gt;easy&lt;/b&gt; to deduce the decryption key from the encryption key. However, if it is practically impossible to deduce the decryption key from the encryption key, then the system is called &lt;b&gt;asymmetric or public key&lt;/b&gt;. One reason for distinguishing between these two types of system should be clear. In order to prevent an interceptor with knowledge of the algorithm from obtaining the plaintext from intercepted ciphertext it is &lt;b&gt;essential that the decryption key should be secret&lt;/b&gt;. Whereas for a symmetric system this necessitates that the encryption key should also be secret, if the system is asymmetric then knowledge of this key is of no practical use to the attacker. Indeed it can be, and usually is, made public. One consequence of this is that there is no need for the sender and receiver of a cryptogram to share any common secrets. In fact there may be no need for them to trust each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a famous principle of cryptography which asserts that the security of a cryptographic system must not depend on keeping secret the cryptographic algorithm it should depend only on keeping secret the decryption key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attack which utilizes the existence of known &lt;b&gt;plaintext and ciphertext pairs&lt;/b&gt; is called a known &lt;b&gt;plaintext attack&lt;/b&gt;. If the plaintext is selected by the attacker then it is a &lt;b&gt;chosen plaintext attack&lt;/b&gt;. Finally, an attack which has direct knowledge only of the ciphertext is known as a &lt;b&gt;ciphertext-only attack&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we assume that our &lt;b&gt;decryption algorithm is known&lt;/b&gt; then there is one obvious method of attack available to any adversary. They could, at least in theory, &lt;b&gt;try each possible decryption key&lt;/b&gt; and ‘hope’ that they identify the correct one. Such an attack is called an &lt;b&gt;exhaustive key search&lt;/b&gt;. However, as we see when we consider some simple examples, unless there is sufficient volume of corresponding plaintext and ciphertext pairs, there may be many incorrect choices for the decryption key which give the correct answers for all the available ciphertext.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Keys: A real life situation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the example we assume that the sender has a present, which he wants to lock in a briefcase with a padlock and send to someone, whom he is not prepared to trust with his own key. Instead the sender instructs the intended receiver to buy his own padlock and key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Step 1:&lt;/b&gt; The sender places the present in the briefcase, which they lock with their padlock and remove their key. They then send the locked briefcase to the receiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the receiver is also unable to obtain the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Step 2:&lt;/b&gt; The receiver locks the briefcase with their own padlock and removes the key. They then return it to the sender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The briefcase is now locked with two padlocks so no one can get the present. The sender uses their own key to remove their padlock from the briefcase and returns the briefcase to the receiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Step 3:&lt;b&gt; The receiver removes their padlock from the briefcase to obtain the present.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;PROBLEM HERE:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this simplistic example we have to admit that the sender has no way of knowing whose padlock is on the briefcase and that it might be possible for an adversary to impersonate the receiver and place their padlock on the briefcase. This is a problem that has to be addressed. The Whose padlock is it?’ question in this briefcase example is similar to the Whose public key is it?’ question that is so important when public key systems are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kerckhoffs’s Principle:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle says that the system should be secure even if the attacker knows all the details about the system with the exception of the secret key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-06-01-at-3-32-32-pm.png?w=739&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Classical Attacks&lt;/b&gt;
•Mathematical Analysis • Brute-Force Attack&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Implementation Attack:&lt;/b&gt;  Try to extract key through reverese engineering or power measurement, e.g., for a banking smart card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Social Engineering:&lt;/b&gt;  E.g., trick a user into giving up his/her password&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Arithmetic Modulo:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing arithmetic modulo m we obtain the integer ring &lt;b&gt;Zm&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An element a ε Zm has a multiplicative inverse &lt;b&gt;only if: gcd (a, m) = 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Ex: We consider the ring Z9 = {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8}
The elements 0, 3, and 6 do not have inverses since they are not coprime to 9. The inverses of the other elements 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, and 8 are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1-1 ≡ 1 mod 9 2-1 ≡ 5 mod 9 4-1 ≡ 7 mod 9 5-1 ≡ 2 mod 9 7-1 ≡ 4 mod 9 8-1 ≡ 8 mod 9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction-to-cryptology&quot;&gt;Introduction to cryptology:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-06-01-at-2-29-31-pm.png?w=739&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptology is defined as the science of making communication incomprehensible to all people except those who have a right to read and understand it. The study of cryptology consists of two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• cryptography, which concerns itself with the secrecy system itself and its design, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• cryptanalysis, which concerns itself with the breaking of the secrecy system above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early signs of encryption in Eqypt in ca. 2000 B.C. Letter-based encryption schemes (e.g., Caesar cipher) popular ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;b&gt;Symmetric ciphers:&lt;/b&gt; All encryption schemes from ancient times until 1976 were symmetric ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;b&gt;Asymmetric ciphers:&lt;/b&gt; In 1976 public-key (or asymmetric) cryptography was openly proposed by Diffie, Hellman and Merkle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• &lt;b&gt;Hybrid Schemes:&lt;/b&gt; The majority of today‘s protocols are hybrid schemes, i.e., the use both symmteric ciphers (e.g., for encryption and message authentication) and asymmetric ciphers (e.g., for key exchange and digital signature).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The encrypted plaintext is called the &lt;b&gt;ciphertext or cryptogram&lt;/b&gt; and the set of rules used to encrypt information plaintext is the encryption algorithm. Normally the operation of this algorithm depends on an &lt;b&gt;encryption key, which is input to the algorithm together with the message&lt;/b&gt;. In order that the recipient can obtain the message from the cryptogram there has to be a decryption algorithm which, when used with the appropriate decryption key, reproduces the plaintext from the ciphertext.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Key&lt;/b&gt; – information that will allow someone to encipher the plaintext and also decipher the cipher text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://rgssmaths.files.wordpress.com/2017/05/screen-shot-2017-06-01-at-2-54-34-pm.png?w=739&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we move the key through a different secure channel from the sender to the receiver. While, the encryption and the decryption functions are kept open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Equations:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encryption equation y = eK(x)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decryption equation x = dK(y)
Encryption and decryption are inverse operations if the same key K is used on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/cryptography/&quot;&gt;Cryptography&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 21, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fractals]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/fractals/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/fractals</id>
  <published>2017-05-27T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-05-27T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Keshav Janyani</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>kjanyani@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Hasn’t symmetry always mesmerized you? Fractals are special objects that are symmetric with respect to scale.
### What are Fractals?
Fractals are beautiful mathematical patterns that are characterized by self-similarity. If a fractal pattern
is zoomed into, the exact same pattern appears. Few popular examples are the Sierpinski Gasket and
the Koch Snowflake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/JReakhhPF0eEE&quot; position=&quot;relative&quot; width=&quot;375&quot; height=&quot;416&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/11Qw9rxGAYniKc&quot; position=&quot;relative&quot; bottom=&quot;416&quot; width=&quot;375&quot; height=&quot;416&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fractal-dimensions&quot;&gt;Fractal Dimensions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fractals are also unique in that Fractal Dimension is not a whole number. As an example, the length of a Koch Curve is infinite while the area is zero. Hence, the dimension of the fractal is greater than one and less than two. Fractal dimensions can also be understood as a measure for space-filing capacity of a pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://fractalfoundation.org/OFCA/dimensioneg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dimension example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now see an example on how to find the dimensions of a fractal: Koch Curve. Before that, consider a non-fractal object as shown and examine the pattern. If we magnify the line by a factor of r=2; its measure (length) increases to 2. If we do the same thing to a square and a cube, the measure increases
by a factor of 4 and 8 respectively. Note that the relation N=r$^{D}$ holds, where N is the number of pieces
(similar to r=1), r is the scaling factor and D is the dimension. Thus $D=\frac{log(N)}{log(r)}$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us try to apply similarly to Koch Curve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/5d/Koch_curve.svg/621px-Koch_curve.svg.png&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scaling it by a factor of r=3, we get;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=0B5WYkNcxlIlDN3Y4MlNYdU1qcFE&quot; alt=&quot;Koch Curve size3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are N=4 pieces of the final object similar to the object or r=1 as shown. Hence, Dimension is $\frac{log(4)}{log(3)}=1.6$
Consider the Sierpinski Gasket&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=0B5WYkNcxlIlDbVdxTHlyZ2lqNFk&quot; alt=&quot;Sierpinski size1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scale it by a factor of r=2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=0B5WYkNcxlIlDNnV2WlZyaktpaEU&quot; alt=&quot;Sierpinski size2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get N=3 pieces of the same size as that of r=1.Hence The Dimension is  $\frac{log(3)}{log(2)}=1.58$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fractals-in-nature&quot;&gt;Fractals in Nature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although perfect Fractals cannot appear in nature because if you zoom further and further, we would
eventually reach molecules and atoms (self-similarity stops at a much higher scale) which are not similar
to the whole fractal; approximate fractals are found in nature having self-similarity over a finite range of
scales. Brownian motion is an example of approximate fractal. Fractals are a very efficient design for
plants to maximize their exposure to sun and cardiovascular systems to most efficiently transport
oxygen to all parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=0B5WYkNcxlIlDVkhDUzRIX29aZWs&quot; alt=&quot;Fractals in nature&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below shows how fractals can appear in mathematical constructs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kbKtFN71Lfs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a Geogebra workspace where you can fiddle around with parameters to get a fractal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe scrolling=&quot;no&quot; title=&quot;Fractals&quot; src=&quot;https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/SEZdQc37/width/800/height/600/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; style=&quot;border:0px;&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mandelbrot-set&quot;&gt;Mandelbrot Set&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mandelbrot was a French and American mathematician who referred to himself as the
“fractalist”. He coined the word “Fractal” and is recognized for his contribution to fractal geometry. The Mandelbrot Set, one of the most famous fractals is the set obtained from
the quadratic recurrence equation $z_{n+1}=z_n^2+C$ with $z_0=C$ ,where points C in the complex
plane for which the orbit of zn does not tend to infinity are in the set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/pb0iuLS5EguxG&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;269&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-study-fractals&quot;&gt;Why study fractals?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Clouds are not spheres, mountains are not cones, coastlines are not circles, and bark is not smooth, nor
does lightning travel in a straight line.”
― Benoît B. Mandelbrot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study of Fractals has applications in a wide range of fields. Fractals are used to model natural objects
like clouds, mountains, etc in Computer science. Fractals are used to create landscapes that are
otherwise impossible with conventional technology in shows like Star Wars and Star trek. Fractals are
commonly used in chaos theory as graphs of chaotic processes are fractals. Hilbert’s Space filling Curve
and other such space-filing curves are fractals. It also finds application in Image Compressing. Certain
algorithms are used to convert parts of images that have resemblance with other parts of the image into
mathematical data called “fractal codes” which are used to recreate the encoded image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=0B5WYkNcxlIlDOFpaZ2t2cHJEYXc&quot; alt=&quot;Computer generated fractal landscape &amp;amp; Hilbert’s Space filing Curve&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a TED talk by Benoit Mandelbrot on” Fractals and the Art of Roughness”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ay8OMOsf6AQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/fractals/&quot;&gt;Fractals&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 27, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Summer of Science]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/summer-of-science/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/summer-of-science</id>
  <published>2017-03-29T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-03-29T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Summer of Science is an initiative by the Maths and Physics Club, to encourage, and help discover, the joy of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Live as if you were to die tomorrow. Learn as if you were to live forever.” - &lt;strong&gt;Mahatma Gandhi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has there been something you wanted to explore, but never been able to, for lack of guidance, or simply been unsure where to start? Anything ranging from Computer Architecture, General Relativity, Cosmology, to Abstract Algebra!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got an idea? Have the enthusiasm? We’ll find you a mentor, with sufficient experience on the topic, to guide you on your quest, for the whole duration of summer – starting the first week of May to the second week of July. It is not required to be present in the institute during the entire period of SoS - the interaction with the mentors will be online, and a report has to be submitted by the second week of July. Learning is best done at your own pace - there is no strict requirement on the minimum content that has to be covered. However, it is very strongly recommended that you focus on SoS for at least 25 days during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report has to be submitted by the end of the summer, tentatively by second week of July..The Reports will be put up on the website! The SoS certificate, with equal standing as that of ITSP, will be awarded on submission of the report. On the swag factor, we’ll be having a group discussion by the beginning of the semester to discuss what we have learned over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Tell me and I forget, teach me and I may remember, involve me and I learn.” &lt;strong&gt;― Benjamin Franklin.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the only prerequisite is enthusiasm. No prior knowledge on the topic is expected, and a broad topic is typically chosen at the start of the summer - the specifics can be figured out along the way!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/summer-of-science/&quot;&gt;The Summer of Science&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on March 29, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum Computing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/quantum-computation/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/quantum-computation</id>
  <published>2017-01-09T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2017-01-09T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Toshi Parmar</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>toshi.tanu08@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following article was written for and published by the annual newsletter of Dept. of Physics, IIT Bombay in collaboration with Insight, the student media body of IITB, in the Autumn semester of my freshmen year (2015). It is aimed at providing a brief info to the latest advancements in the field of quantum computing and what lies ahead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.doc.ic.ac.uk/~ids/dotdot/misc/images/dilbert-dt970322_295.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Quantum Computation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-new-hope&quot;&gt;A New Hope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our story begins with a team of researchers at The University of New South Wales(UNSW), Australia, led by Andrew Dzurak who have successfully 
accomplished the making of a two qubit logic gate in silicon, which is a crucial hurdle overcome in making quantum computers
a reality. “What we have is a game changer,” says team leader Prof. Dzurak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve demonstrated a two qubit logic gate the central building block of a quantum computer and, significantly, done it in silicon. 
Because we use essentially the same device technology as existing computer chips, we believe it will be much easier to manufacture 
a fullscale processor chip than for any of the leading designs, which rely on more exotic technologies.”
The key idea behind the working of the UNSW team has been the morphing of normal transistors, into defining quantum bits or ‘qubits’, 
by ensuring that each transistor has a single electron associated with it, and representing the binary equivalent of numbers 0 and 1 
by spin of the electron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentence makes sense quite ephemerally, so let’s deconstruct the concept in lyman’s language and restore freedom to our bound curiosity…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-very-begining&quot;&gt;The Very Begining&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially the concept of quantum computing involves use of quantum bits or ‘qubits’ instead of conventional bits in boolean algebra, 
that can be coupled in a scalable manner to make up one and two qubit logic gates. 
The numerous physical realisations of qubits, single photons, trapped ions, silicon and semiconductor quantum dots, 
single defects or atoms in diamond etc. have to be sufficiently fault tolerant and conserved under time evolution, 
with discrete and spaced eigenvalues that can be mapped onto an effective spin 1/2 system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideation for representing qubits as the spin of an electron was primarily proposed in 1968, 
and sparked up with eminent physicist Richard Feynman proposing the possibility of a quantum computer in 1982.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;that-which-makes-all-the-difference&quot;&gt;That which makes all the difference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The edge that a quantum system has over the conventional is the property of entanglement and superposition of states, 
i.e. a qubit’s existence is governed by superposition of the two basis states that denote conventional bits 0 and 1, 
mathematically, a linear combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/6b/Bloch_sphere.svg/237px-Bloch_sphere.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bloch Sphere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bloch sphere shown in the article, is a representation of a qubit with associated probability amplitudes, 
with the two basis states represented in standard Dirac notation (The braket notation). 
Thus considering two interacting qubits, four possible combinations yield, each weighed by a coefficient 
that denotes the probability of existence of the system in that state.
To specify a combination of two conventional bits, two information are coded, the value of both the bits, 
while for the quantum system four information, the four coefficients. 
Thus the information represented by an ‘n’ qubit system is exponentially large in comparison with its classical counterpart, 
the former is essentially two raised to the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-the-world-is-not-all-cupcakes-and-rainbows&quot;&gt;But the world is not all cupcakes and rainbows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of superposition cascades down to one of its basis states on observation,
termed as the collapse of the governing Schrodinger wave function, essentially leading to us losing our data that boasted
of exponentially large capacities to normal bit sized information.
Thus, here lies the spinner, specific algorithms have to be applied to extract specific information out of a quantum system.
Many such brilliant minds have risen to the occasion, among them, notably and famed are Peter Shor (Shor’s Algorithm, 1994), 
Daniel Simon (Simon’s Algorithm, 1994) and Lov K. Grover (Grover’s Algorithm, 1996).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at what specific information can be extracted out -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shor’s algorithm is a quantum algorithm that addresses the problem of discrete logarithms and integer factorisation, 
a problem so intricate that our public key cryptography schemes like the RSA rely on the computational intractability 
in factoring large numbers for the most advanced classical computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon’s algorithm deals with the computational analysis of decision tree complexity and solves the problem exponentially 
faster than any known classical algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grover’s algorithm addresses database search, i.e. given a unique output produced by a black box function 
(A function with unknown formulation but known mapping) it figures out the input with high probability, 
addressing the problem in quadratically fewer queries than classical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many more such algorithms exist, attacking with brute force, the issues that lie beyond the scope of classical computers.
Another problem is that many of the quantum algorithms give probabilistic solutions, solutions with probability very close to one, 
and which can be improved upon by repeated iterations but nevertheless its probabilistic. 
Many others however, are fully deterministic and hence efficacious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantum computers can only respond to specific algorithms and tasks exponentially efficiently than classical, thus, 
they are not the substitute for them, but an aid, for more technological and advanced sector. 
Not every task that a normal personal computer does can be effectively performed with them.
So wish the genie to show you a movie, and quantum computer would be useless trash. Wish to crack security codes for all online credit
transfers, ye ol’ quantum computer would watch the world burn as it decrypts transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-not-so-farther-difficulties-ahead&quot;&gt;Further, not-so-farther difficulties ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big hurdle now is to remove decoherence from the system, isolating the system from the
surroundings, cutting down its interactions that make the system decohere, and to do so
economically and feasibly. Decoherence is irreversible and nonunitary and thus must be
controlled if not eradicated. Currently superconducting qubits can be configured to remove
setting in of significant decoherence in physically avoidable time lag, which typically ranges 
between the order of nanoseconds to seconds at low temperatures, by cooling the qubit to 20milli kelvin or lower temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that is now faced is to scale this system up to vast numbers of stable qubit registers or “q-registers”, 
quantum mechanical analogues of classical processor registers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless a very efficient way is developed, optimum working is an impossibility.
In this direction, Prof. Dzurak notes that the team has “recently patented a design for full scale
quantum computer chip that would allow for millions of our qubits, all doing the same kind of calculations 
we’ve just experimentally demonstrated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UNSW team’s research breakthrough has attacked three of the major requirements -&lt;br /&gt;
1) qubits that can be initialised to arbitrary values, 
2) qubits with successful readout fidelities, 
3) a universal CNOT quantum gate, faster than the decoherence time of the system, 
with the fabrication process compatible with standard Complementary Metal Oxide Semiconductor (CMOS) technology that already exists
 for manufacturing classical Si based semiconductor chips.
Future experiments by this team will include improvements to facilitate full two qubit tomography. 
Improvement by lowering the sensitivity to electrical noise is also targeted. 
Though the two qubit system represents the smallest scalable system so far, it is consistent with current transistor sizes, offering the prospect of realizing a largescale
quantum processor using the same silicon manufacturing technologies that have enabled the current information age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, on a more tender note,
“Computers are physical objects, and computations are physical processes.
What computers can or cannot compute is determined by the laws of physics alone.”
– David Deutsch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we mustn’t lose faith. More breakthroughs are yet to arrive!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/quantum-computation/&quot;&gt;Quantum Computing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on January 09, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Universe and Beyond!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/universe/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/universe</id>
  <published>2016-08-20T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-20T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Is our universe really infinite? If you keep going in some direction in a spacecraft will you see some magical force field and a sign board saying “End of the Universe, Keep Out!” (Or rather, keep in? :P). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://ichef.bbci.co.uk/wwfeatures/wm/live/1280_640/images/live/p0/3x/sw/p03xsw49.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Universe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can say for certain that the universe is either finite or infinite (Big deal, who can’t say that? But wait, there’s more to it!). In an infinite universe, you can go on and on in your spaceship and you’ll never come across a boundary – you’ll just see more stars, galaxies, and maybe get to see some extra-terrestrial life. However, in a finite universe, you won’t come across a boundary- you’ll end up exactly where you started! You can associate this funny behaviour with the curvature of space time. Physicists are not yet sure about the geometry of our universe – it can be open (infinite), closed (finite) or flat (we’ll get to that later!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into more details, we need to be familiar with the concept of critical density – in an expanding universe, if its average density turns out to be higher than a particular ‘critical’ value, it would collapse under its own gravity. Otherwise, it could expand forever (Slightly reminiscent of the escape velocity of the Earth – if you throw something hard enough, it’ll never come back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the exact geometry depends on the average density of the universe (This is predicted by the Friedmann equation, arguably the most important result in cosmology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It so turns out that if the average density of the universe is greater than this particular critical density (around $ 9.47x10^{-27} Kg/m^3 $ ), it would result in a closed finite universe, and an infinite open universe otherwise. If the density exactly matches the critical density, the universe would be flat – you can say that the space ship will go on for ever, or that it will come to the point where it started after traveling for an infinite time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can draw a two dimensional analogy to the closed and open universe. The closed universe is like a sphere – you’ll end up where you started if you keep going ‘in a straight line’. Since we are able to observe this from a 3- dimensional geometry, we can see the curvature of the two dimensional space we cooked up – but any two dimensional beings in our two dimensional universe would not be able to detect the ‘curvature’. Now the two dimensional analogue of an open universe is a saddle shape.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/40/Saddle_point.png&quot; alt=&quot;Saddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, any two dimensional beings would not be able to detect the curvature of their universe, just as we are not able to see any possible curvature in our universe. The two dimensional analogy of the flat universe is, well, flat. We see something exceedingly interesting here – the flat universe supports Euclidean geometry. In curved geometries, non-Euclidean geometry prevails. For example, in a closed universe, the ratio of the circumference to the diameter of a circle need not be the familiar value of pi – to put it better, the ratio of the circumference to the diameter of a circle in a curved geometry need not satisfy the equation $ e^{ix} +1 = 0 $. Again, it’s difficult to imagine this in a curved 3 dimensional geometry, but it’s easier in a curved two dimensional space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since all distances are measured in the plane, the radius of the circle in the closed universe is more than that in a flat geometry, and less in an infinite geometry. The value of pi is, hence more than that for a Euclidean geometry in an open universe and less in a closed universe. The same result follows in a three dimensional curved geometry. Hard to believe, but true. (See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedmann%E2%80%93Lema%C3%AEtre%E2%80%93Robertson%E2%80%93Walker_metric&quot;&gt;Riemann Walker metric&lt;/a&gt;, and the video below, which nicely explains it. It’s hard to intuitively understand the deviation of the value of pi from its familiar Euclidean value in three dimension, and is best described mathematically.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/n1kK5BjEh9E&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the angles of a triangle need not add up to 180 0 . It is more than 180 0 for a closed geometry and less than that for an open one. The closed universe is said to have ‘Positive’ curvature and the open one has ’Negative’ curvature. The flat universe has zero curvature. The angles of a triangle sum up to exactly 180 0 in that case.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://wmap.gsfc.nasa.gov/media/990006/990006_2048.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Curvature&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is our universe open, closed or flat? All you have to do is measure the density, right? Trouble is, the measured value of average density of the universe is extremely close to the calculated critical density (taking into account dark matter and dark energy). It is not yet possible to say with certainty whether the universe is flat, open or closed. The best measured value of the ‘density parameter’, or the ratio of the actual density of the universe to the critical density is often quoted as around. (Damn! In that case the universe could be flat, open or closed!). Well, at least that explains why Euclidean geometry seems to hold in real life, and the angles of a triangle seem to add up to a hundred and eighty degrees. The curvature of our present universe is too small to detect in a small scale - sort of like why we’re not able to see the curvature of the Earth from its surface. (But then again, if the universe was indeed strongly curved, would the curved geometry have seemed natural and intuitive to us? Would Euclidean geometry seem alien? We can only wonder…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the universe so ‘flat’? Why is the density parameter so close to one? (You might want to see this awesome video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MTUsOWtxKKA&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  There are some exotic and beautiful ideas like the theory of inflation, which seek to explain this observation (Inflation is another story, for another day!). The idea of inflation explains the flatness problem, the horizon problem and some other peculiar observations. It also predicts the existence of other universes, with possibly different laws of physics, separated by high energy ‘False Vacuum’. But so far, inflation has not made any predictions which could be tested. (The Theory of General Relativity was accepted only after the gravitational lensing of the light from a distant star by the sun was experimentally observed. The lensing effect was predicted by GR long before it was ever observed). However, inflationary models of the early universe do predict large scale gravitational waves, which, if detected, could provide direct proof of inflation. (The recently detected gravitational waves were the result of a particularly violent astronomical event – the kind of gravitational waves predicted by inflationary models are far more feeble, and hence harder to detect.). That is another motivation for building highly sensitive gravitational wave detectors – an active area of research in experimental physics. Inflation is an elegant and beautiful idea, which many physicists are eager to accept – but due to the lack of observable predictions, it’s still more like an idea, and not a theorem. The next decade will undoubtedly see advances in gravitational wave astronomy, and possibly provide conformation for inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you might have noticed that I have ignored dark energy completely here. Well, it has now been observed that the universe is currently expanding exponentially – for the past few billion years. Dark energy, like inflation, is also predicted to be the outcome of a field – but one much weaker than that caused inflation. But it is quite possible that the exponential expansion due to dark energy might come to an end, just like that of inflation did. (If I may venture to say, likely. Can’t expect that to happen anytime soon, though. Dark energy has been doing its funny business for at least the last few billion years. It is also quite possible that this exponential expansion can go on for ever, eliminating the possibility of a big crunch. So much for looking forward to the boom and fancy lights.) And whatever we dreamt up still holds true, the universe might be closed or open, hyperbolic or spherical, all depending on its current density. Neither inflation nor dark energy can ‘flip’ its geometry – merely push it towards flatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curious about the mathematical formalism of the Riemann Walker metric? Or the exact deviation of pi from its ‘Euclidean’ value? Dark energy and inflation? &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B89M-PMv8EXlRUozVW43RWJtTkE&quot;&gt; &lt;u&gt;Read on &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to find out more!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/universe/&quot;&gt;The Universe and Beyond!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blackhole Information Paradox]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/blackhole-paradox/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/blackhole-paradox</id>
  <published>2016-07-24T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-07-24T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Toshi Parmar</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>toshi.tanu08@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the baffle still remain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://space-facts.com/wp-content/uploads/black-hole.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blackhole&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a talk given on Aug ‘15 at a conference held at Stockholm$^{[1]}$; Stephen Hawking, the well-celebrated british physicist, proposed a resolution of the infamous Information loss paradox, a child of his own theory of Hawking Radiation $^{[2][3]}$ that overturned the widely perpetuated belief that nothing escapes from a black hole’s event horizon. In the interim, this left most of his contemporaries bemused since his theory had no mathematical backbone. A rigorous paper$^{[4]}$ collaborated by Hawking, Malcolm &amp;amp; Strominger in the January of ‘16, humorously entitled ‘Soft Hair on Black Holes’, attempts to pave a mathematical map to resolve the paradox once and for all. But Hawking et al conclude$^{[4]}$ that they’ve just introduced fresh &amp;amp; concrete tools to address the paradox and a complete description still remains an open challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-the-paradox&quot;&gt;What exactly IS the paradox?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information loss paradox is yet another acclaimed scenario where Quantum Mechanics, describing the subatomic world with the highest precision and General Relativity, equally successful at the cosmic scale, act stubbornly incompatible$^{[10]}$.
General Relativity implies that once a system ‘falls’$^{[5]}$ in the black hole, any information regarding the system can not affect an outside observer, thus for all practical purposes the information is irretrievable. Notice, that we use irretrievable instead of destroyed, i.e. it doesn’t posses a problem if the black hole remains an ever absorbing body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hawking-radiation&quot;&gt;The Hawking Radiation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1975, due to a remarkable connection made by Hawking$^{[6]}$ and Beckenstein$^{[7]}$ between Thermodynamics, Quantum Mechanics and Black Holes, Hawking Radiation came into picture which collapsed the possibility of everlasting black holes to null.
Hawking Radiation stated that black holes, in fact, aren’t as black as we expected them to be. Courtesy to locally small quantum effects$^{[2]}$, (which are ignored in the process of formation and evolution of black holes since the radius of curvature of spacetime outside the event horizon is very large compared to the Planck length$^{[11]}$, the length scale on which quantum fluctuations of the metric are expected to be of order unity) add up to produce a significant effect over the lifetime of the Universe. This simply implies that any black hole will create and emit particles such as neutrinos or photons at just the rate that one would expect if the black hole of M solar masses was similar to a blackbody, with temperature of about $6 × 10^{-8}$/M kelvins$^{[8]}$.
The fact that a black hole will emit photons when none escape is indigestible.
In layman language$^{[9]}$, Quantum Mechanics capacitates a constant potential for “virtual” Particle - Antiparticle pair to be created and annihilated, leaving a net zero state. Same phenomenon at the knife edge of the event horizon permits a possibility when one escapes, while the other plunges immediately into the black hole. Rather than instant annihilation, the “virtual” particle becomes real and escapes; making a petty energy drain on the black hole. The rate at which the energy dissipates from a black hole of M solar masses spares a massive 1071M3 seconds$^{[8]}$ as any black hole’s life period. Any such black hole of mass less than 1015 g would have evaporated by now. Near the end of its life the rate of emission would be very high and about 1030 erg would be released in the last 0.1 s$^{[2]}$. This is a fairly small explosion by astronomical standards but it is equivalent to about 1 million 1 Mton hydrogen bombs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aftermaths-of-hawking-radiation-theory&quot;&gt;Aftermaths of Hawking Radiation Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand why the information loss paradox is a problem, we need first to understand what it is.
Let’s design a thought experiment where a quantum system in pure state enters a black hole. The no-hair (or more aptly, three-hair) theorem$^{[15]}$ compels Hawking radiation to be completely independent of the state of the quantum system entering the black hole. Because part of the information about the state of the system is lost down the hole, the final situation is represented by a density matrix$^{[11]}$ rather than a pure quantum state (which it was, originally). In quantum physics, a scattering matrix or S-matrix is a unitary matrix$^{[12]}$ that maps the scattering channels (the quantum states of system before or after the collision). The scenario could have been picturised as the initial pure state quantum system interacting with a boundary condition and the Hawking radiation as the final scattering channel. But since the transformation from a pure quantum state to a density matrix is non-unitary, this means there is no Scattering-matrix$^{[13]}$ for the process of black-hole formation and evaporation. Or to say, the black hole has performed a non-unitary transformation on the state of system!$^{[14]}$  As you may recall, non-unitary evolution is not allowed to occur naturally in quantum theory because it fails to preserve probability &amp;amp; reversibility.
In layman terms what we start with is a pure state and a black hole of mass M.  What we end up with is a mixed state and a black hole of mass M.  In transforming between a mixed state and a pure state, one must throw away information.  For instance, in our example we took a state described by a set of eigenvalues and coefficients, a large set of numbers, and transformed it into a state described by temperature, one number.  All the other structure of the state was lost in the transformation.
In the face of such evolution, quantum mechanics falls apart, and we are faced with a dilemma.  Do black holes really defy the tenets of quantum theory, or have we missed something in our thought experiment.
Thus, therein lies a paradox!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-way-ahead&quot;&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possible Solutions To The Fate of Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There have been many proposed solutions to the paradox, each equally bewildering as another. They are generally classified first into radical options, which require a quantum theory of gravity which has large deviations from semi-classical physics on macroscopic scales, such as non-locality or endowing horizons with special properties not seen in the semiclassical approximation, and conservative options, which do not need such help. Among the conservative options, it is argued that restoring unitary evolution relies on elimination of singularities.$^{[16]}$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hawking’s leads : Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
AdS-CFT correspondence theory$^{[17]}$, a theory launched in 1993, brought what is called as a Holographic Principle into center play in string theory. Holographic principle bestows same properties to universe as its root word indicates, a dimensional reduction. A hologram, which we encounter is a 2-D representation of a 3-D object. Holographic principle was first introduced by G. ‘t Hooft in 1933 as an attempt to a solution to the Information loss paradox and the widely proclaimed war he and L. Susskind had waged against hawking’s earlier claims that information is indeed lost. ‘T Hooft opined$^{[18]}$ that the requirement that physical phenomena associated with gravitational collapse should be duly reconciled with the postulates of quantum mechanics implies that at a Planckian scale our world is not 3+1 dimensional. Rather, the observable degrees of freedom can best be described as if they were Boolean variables defined on a two-dimensional lattice, evolving with time. This observation, deduced from not much more than unitarity, entropy and counting arguments, implies severe restrictions on possible models of quantum gravity. This dimensional reduction implies more constraints than the freedom we have in constructing models. This is the main reason why so-far no completely consistent mathematical models of quantum black holes have been found.
A year later, L. Susskind published a paper, ‘The World as A Hologram’$^{[19]}$, backing up ‘t Hooft’s theory. In July ‘04 Hawking conceded the bet since the AdS/CFT correspondence has shown there is no information loss. Then Hawking set working on the question : How does the information of the quantum state of the infalling particles re-emerge in the outgoing radiation?$^{[1]}$ He proposes that the information is stored, not in the interior of the black hole (as one might expect), but on its boundary, the event horizon. This is a form of holography. Classically, a black hole is independent of its past history. This is also true in the quantum domain. How then can a black hole emit the information about the particles that fell in? The answer, as explained above, is that the information is stored in a supertranslation associated with the shift of the horizon that the ingoing particles caused (Ingoing particles increase the mass of the black hole resulting into an outward shift in the horizon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;supertranslation&lt;/em&gt;, in layman terms, are the result of a kind of symmetry. In Strominger’s terms$^{[20]}$, Individual light rays can’t talk to each other—if you’re riding on a light ray, causality prevents you from talking to somebody riding on an adjacent light ray. So these light rays are not tethered together. You can slide them up and down relative to one another. That sliding is called a super-translation. It turns out that adding a soft graviton at the event horizon has an alternate description as a super-translation in which you move some of these light rays back and forth relative to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;supertranslations&lt;/em&gt; form a hologram of the ingoing particles at the horizon(For each particle that goes in, a soft-graviton is added). Thus, the jargon soft hair. The varying shifts along each generator of the horizon leave an imprint on the outgoing particles in a chaotic but deterministic manner. There is no loss of information and Information can be recovered in principle, but it is lost for all practical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1509.01147v1.pdf&quot;&gt;The Information Paradox for Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v248/n5443/abs/248030a0.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Explosions?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://inspirehep.net/record/101338?ln=en&quot;&gt;Particle Creation by Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1601.00921v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[5] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Event_horizon&quot;&gt;Event Horizon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[6] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/pdf/10.1103/PhysRevD.14.2460&quot;&gt;Breakdown of Predictability in Gravitational Collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[7] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.7.2333&quot;&gt;Black Holes &amp;amp; Entropy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/hawking.html&quot;&gt;Hawking Radiation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[9] &lt;a href=&quot;https://starguyspeaks.wordpress.com/2016/02/21/on-steven-hawkings-new-theory-of-black-holes/&quot;&gt;Wordpress Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[10] &lt;a href=&quot;http://theory.caltech.edu/people/jhs/strings/str115.html&quot;&gt;The Final Contradiction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[11] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/rmp/pdf/10.1103/RevModPhys.29.74&quot;&gt;Description of States in Quantum Mechanics by Density Matrix and Operator Techniques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[12] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Unitary_operator&quot;&gt;Unitary Operator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[13] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/S-matrix&quot;&gt;S-Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[14] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/info_loss.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Information Loss Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[15] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/No-hair_theorem&quot;&gt;No-Hair Theorem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[16] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/0901.3156v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Conservative solutions to the black hole Information loss problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[17] &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1501.00007.pdf&quot;&gt;The AdS/CFT Correspondence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[18] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/gr-qc/9310026&quot;&gt;Dimensional Reduction in Quantum Gravity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[19] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/hep-th/9409089&quot;&gt;The World as Hologram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[20] &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/dark-star-diaries/stephen-hawking-s-new-black-hole-paper-translated-an-interview-with-co-author-andrew-strominger/&quot;&gt;Interview by co-author Andrew Strominger&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/blackhole-paradox/&quot;&gt;Blackhole Information Paradox&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brain's Positioning System]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/brain-positioning/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/brain-positioning</id>
  <published>2016-06-06T05:31:22+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-06-06T05:31:22+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;ever-wondered-whats-happening-in-our-brains-when-we-get-lost-or-explore-a-new-place-the-nobel-prize-in-physiology-for-the-year-2014-was-awarded-for-some-of-the-answers-to-this-problem-which-had-been-puzzling-scientists-for-almost-a-century&quot;&gt;Ever wondered what’s happening in our brains when we get lost or explore a new place? The Nobel Prize in Physiology for the year 2014 was awarded for some of the answers to this problem which had been puzzling scientists for almost a century.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the GPS in our phones and cars, our brain has a sophisticated positioning system. The brain integrates sensory data and knowledge of our current position to judge where we are headed. Only when we are lost or suffer from neurodegenerative diseases do we realise how critical our positioning system is to our survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracking and positioning systems of the mammalian brain was being studied for a long time. For example, the simple roundworm (Caenorhabditis elegans), with just 302 neurons, finds its way around solely by olfactory signals. It follows the path of an increasing or decreasing odour gradient. Honeybees, on the other hand, calculate its position by integrating its direction and speed of movement, without keeping track of landmarks or external cues. Vertebrates have even more sophisticated positioning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recent research in the area reveal neural maps in the brains of mammals, which are collections of neurons which fire in specific patterns corresponding to the surroundings and the animal’s position in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/2014/advanced-medicineprize2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Dr. John M. O’Keefe, Dr. May-Britt Moser and Dr. Edvard I. Moser for their discoveries of nerve cells in the brain that enable a sense of place and navigation.
Until the 1930s, research done on lab mice in mazes led to the belief that they memorised a long sequence of lefts and rights to find their way around. Edward C Tolman, physiology professor at the University of California from 1918 to 1954, observed the animals take shortcuts or make detours that would not be expected had they just memorised one long sequence of behaviour. This led to the hypothesis that the rats formed a sort of mental map of its surroundings, corresponding to the spatial geometry around it. Tolman’s ideas remained controversial for decades.
His ideas did not gain much ground up until the 1950s, when it became possible to insert electrodes into the brains of awake mammals to record firing patterns of individual neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cell fires when it triggers an action potential- a short change in the potential difference across the cell membrane.
Dr. John M. O’Keefe studied the brain’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippocampus&quot;&gt;hippocampus&lt;/a&gt;, a region in the brain associated with memory and spatial navigation (On a side note, the Hippocampus is one of the first regions to be affected by the Alzheimer’s disease). He inserted electrodes into a rat’s Hippocampus, and noticed that certain cells fired when the rat was at a particular location. He called them ‘Place cells’. It was seen that the firing pattern of a handful of such place cells precisely identified the animal’s location. In 1978, O’Keefe and his colleague suggested that place cells were an integral part of the mental map Tolman envisaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuroscientists of that era speculated that the hippocampus was too far removed from the sensory cortex (The part of the brain which handles the sensory inputs) to process their information in any meaningful way that could be understood by simple electrodes. O’Keefe’s observations dashed that speculation. It was then hypothesised that the area where place cells were located, namely the CA1 region, in the hippocampus received its location cues from other parts of the hippocampus rather than directly from the sensory cortex.
To verify the hypothesis, O’Keefe and his colleagues disrupted the communication channels between the CA1 region and the region of the hippocampus known to feed information to the CA1. Surprisingly, the neurons in the CA1 fired as before, when the rat reached specific locations. The inescapable conclusion was that the CA1 received its location cues from the entorhinal cortex, an adjoining area of the brain with a direct interface with the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrodes were inserted into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entorhinal_cortex&quot;&gt;entorhinal cortex&lt;/a&gt;, and the firing patterns studied. The cells over there fired much like the place cells, but a single cell also happened to fire at multiple locations! This observation was made in 2002.
By 2005, O’Keefe and his team observed something spectacular about the firing patterns- the locations at which one particular cell fired were the vertices of a regular hexagon! These cells were dubbed grid cells. It was soon apparent that the entire enclosure where the rat was kept was divided into hexagonal grids. As these grid cells were further studied, more patterns were observed- the grid cells in the dorsal side fires at compact hexagons, while those lower down in the ventral side fired at hexagons of larger edge. The different layers of grid cells in the entorhinal cortex fired at hexagons of different size, each layer forming one with approximately 1.4 times the edge length of the hexagon in the layer above. This is strongly reminiscent of the smaller squares and the bigger ones in the Cartesian coordinates.
For example, the top layer fired at hexagons 30 to 35 cm in length, the next layer at 42 to 49 cm, and so on. The lower layers represented hexagons several meters across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direction cells and Border cells were also discovered in the entorhinal cortex – the direction cells fire when the rodent faces a particular direction, and the border cells fire when the rat is facing a wall. The firing patterns seemed to reflect the distance from the wall or the edge of an enclosure. In 2008, another long sought out cell was discovered- the speed cells. The firing rates of these cells increased in proportion to its running speed. These cells were believed to provide the grid cells updated information on the rodent’s position.
It was observed that the place cells in the hippocampus rapidly assumes a new location to fire as soon as the rat was put in a new enclosure. However, the grid cells was found to fire at analogous positions in the new enclosure. The grid cells, in some sense, formed a coordinate system that did not change from one enclosure to the other. The firing patterns from the entorhinal cortex was imported to the hippocampus and used to link the place cells to a particular location.
It is now believed that the hippocampus stores not just the position, but also the events that occur at that particular place. Particulars about an event are fused with the coordinates and are laid down in the animal’s memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;However, the scientific world is still pretty much in the dark as to how this information is used by the rest of the brain’s systems or the evolutionary origins of this intricate mechanism. The location systems of the brain and the mechanisms of memory formation will undoubtedly be a fascinating area of research for many years to come.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/brain-positioning/&quot;&gt;Brain&#39;s Positioning System&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on June 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Memristors and the Future of Computing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/memristors/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/memristors</id>
  <published>2016-05-31T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-05-31T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Dhruv Ilesh Shah</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>dhruv.ilesh@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome the days of a new kind of electronic device.. All hail the memristor, a device that could revolutionarise the world of computing by implementing wonderful technology!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1965, Gordon Moore predicted that the number of transistors in a dense integrated circuit doubles approximately every two years, and since then every manufacturer has been fighting hard to keep up with the Moore’s Law. With the scale of transistor entering sub-20nm, this number is saturating and Moore’s Law has begun to fail us. So what have the scientists and researchers got us? Behold the &lt;i&gt; &lt;b&gt;Memristor&lt;/b&gt;  (a portmanteau of the words memory and resistor)!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original concept for memristors, as conceived in 1971 by Professor Leon Chua at the University of California, Berkeley, was a passive, non-linear, two-terminal electrical component that linked electric charge and magnetic flux. Since then, the definition of memristor has been broadened to include any form of non-volatile memory that is based on resistance switching, which increases the flow of current in one direction and decreases the flow of current in the opposite direction and has since then been thought of as the fourth fundamental electrical component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memristors constitute a special type of memory, called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistive_random-access_memory&quot;&gt; ReRAM &lt;/a&gt; or resistive RAM, which works by altering the resistance across a dielectric. The outlook of memristors as memory devices started in 1996, when Stanley Williams, the founding director of the Quantum Science Research Laboratory at Hewlett-Packard, began to look for memory devices that are defect intolerant at the nano scale. And what better way to make a device defect-intolerant than too employ the defects themselves for the job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; How Memristors Work :&lt;/b&gt; Instead of electrons, memristors use ions as the means of storing information. As the current passes, the holes and defects enable ions of informations to pass through with much greater speed and efficiency - way beyond 1 and 0, to 2, 3 and so on. These levels can be treated as distinct and the demarcation be carried out with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; What Does This Mean? &lt;/b&gt; At a lower power consumption than a transistor, a memristor can have multiple levels of representing data (upto 6 levels have been achieved), thus reducing the number of memristors required to perform the same task and who knows - the computer may actually become equipped with base-10 memory soon enough! For example, the largest unsigned binary 64-bit ­integer—18,446,744,073,709,551,615—could be held in 20 bits instead of 64. This not only reduces the number of transistors used, but also the complexity of circuits and ease of NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A memristor is often compared to an imaginary pipe that carries water. When the water flows in one direction, the pipe’s diameter expands and allows the water to flow faster – but when the water flows in the opposite direction, the pipe’s diameter contracts and slows the water’s flow down. If the water is shut off, the pipe retains its diameter until the water is turned back on. To continue the analogy, when a  memristor’s power is shut off, the memristor retains its resistance value. This would mean that if power to a computer was cut off with a hard shut down,  all the applications and documents that were open before the shut down would still be right there the screen when the computer was restarted. Isn’t that cool? Although we have been able to cut down the leakage current in conventional transistors, we cannot dare imagine making them as efficient as a prototype of a memristor! This would mean a big revolution in computing, and the best part is that it could be market-ready much before Quantum Computers (which use qubits to store more data-per-bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see how the non-volatile nature and resistive-switching is achieved, check out this video by Stanley Williams: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rvA5r4LtVnc&quot;&gt; The 6 Minute Memristor Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact Hewlett-Packard has a whole unit devoted to developing ‘The Machine’, &lt;em&gt;using electrons for processing, photons for communication, and ions for storage&lt;/em&gt;, expected to be completed by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Rupp, a Professor of electrochemical materials at ETH Zurich,is working with IBM to build a memristor-based machine. Memristors, she points out, function in a way that is similar to a human brain: “Unlike a transistor, which is based on binary codes, a memristor can have multi-levels. You could have several states, let’s say zero, one half, one quarter, one third, and so on, and that gives us a very powerful new perspective on how our computers may develop in the future,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a shift in computing methodology would allow us to create “smart” computers that operate in a way reminiscent of the synapses in our brains. Free from the limitations of the 0s and 1s, these more powerful computers would be able to learn and make decisions, ultimately getting us one step closer to creating human-like artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The outcome of this revolution would only be evident by the next decade, but the fact that nano-electronics has enabled us to revolutionarise the micro-electronics industry is a clear signal - to cope up with our growing computing needs, to explore the vastness of Universe, the path goes from within the Nano World! Memristors and Qubits are all set to power the upcoming generations in unfolding the mysteries of our creation, existence and the universe (multiple of them, in fact!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/memristors/&quot;&gt;Memristors and the Future of Computing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flexagons]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/flexagons/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/flexagons</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Parth Jatakia</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io</uri>
    <email>parth.jatakia@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Flexagons are paper polygons, folded from straight or crooked strips of paper, which have the fascinating property of changing their faces when they are “flexed”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began in the fall of 1939. Arthur H. Stone, a 23-year-old graduate student from England, in residence at Princeton University on a mathematics fellowship, had just trimmed an inch from his American notebook sheets to make them fit his English binder. For amusement he began to fold the trimmed-off strips of paper in various ways, and one of the figures he made turned out to be particularly intriguing.
Here’s the video to make a simple hexaflexagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VIVIegSt81k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point Stone found the structure so interesting that he showed his paper models to friends in the graduate school. Soon “flexagons” were appearing in profusion at the lunch and dinner tables. A “Flexagon Committee” was organized to probe further into the mysteries of flexigation. The other members besides Stone were Bryant Tuckerman, a graduate student of mathematics; Richard P. Feynman, a graduate student in physics; and John W. Tukey, a young mathematics instructor.
Tuckerman quickly discovered that the simplest way to bring out all the faces of any flexagon was to keep flexing it at the same corner until it refused to open, then to shift to an adjacent corner. This procedure, known as the “Tuckerman traverse,” will bring up the six faces of a hexahexa in a cycle of 12 flexes, but 1,2 and 3 turn up three times as often as 4, 5 and 6. A convenient way to diagram a Tuckerman traverse is shown in Figure 4, the arrows indicating the order in which the faces are brought into view. This type of diagram can be applied usefully to the traversing of any type of flexagon. When the model is turned over, a Tuckerman traverse runs the same cycle in reverse order.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-duGlEV1ddCw/VymMKE9pabI/AAAAAAAAC3c/XlD-a4OvfcE26j6P_9Ya0Ia2gcMR_1AEQCLcB/s1600/flexagon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flexagon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below gives a great visual explanation of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/paQ10POrZh8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now after trying out the simple ones, if you’d want to achieve pro level…..These are some documents you can refer to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mathematical investigation of Flexagons can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://delta.cs.cinvestav.mx/~mcintosh/comun/tflexagon/tflexagon.pdf&quot;&gt;Theory of Flexagons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also details about more complicated structures can be found out in the following link. Also you will find some papers written on flexagon on this website (though written in russian).: http://www.flexagon.net/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also if you are a foodie this video will be a heaven for you..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTwrVAbV56o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/blog/flexagons/&quot;&gt;Flexagons&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>